Hi everyone, today we'll be going over how I did this effect in Touch Designer
using
point clouds and tops.
So here I used MediaPipe to control morphing, but for the sake of simplicity, we'll
just
use our keyboard.
So if you hold down the one key on your keyboard and release, it will morph in the
exact same
way as the demo video.
We'll also just use two, but you can use as many point clouds as you like and you
can
use whatever models you like as well.
So for a quick overview of the project, we are going to learn how to create an instancing
network using positions and color data.
We're going to set up a little system to control the particles exploding and then
morphing
back into place smoothly, how to make a quick little cage for the particles, and
some really
simple post-processing to create this really cool effect.
So without further ado, let's get started.
Alright, so the first thing we're going to want to do is import our point cloud
file.
So hit tab, and then because we're using tops, select the point file in, and then
this way
you can add your point cloud file.
It's important to note that if you hit red, green, and blue, you'll have these
options,
but not all point cloud files have that.
The general gist is for red, green, and blue, it's probably going to be either XYZ,
RGB,
or red, green, blue.
Select one of those for these.
But for today, I'm just going to copy and paste mine in because I already have them.
So yeah, these don't look like the models, but that's fine.
The first thing we are going to need to figure out is the sort of number problem.
What I mean by that is if you double click and then press info, you'll see that
there
are 403,225 pixels.
For the second model, there are not that many, there are less.
So why does this matter?
So for instancing, we can think of it like particle number one has sort of its
position
data and eventually its color data.
When we morph them, we need to give it an instruction of like, hey, particle one,
instead
of being here, I want to move you to some other location with some other color and
that's
fine.
However, as soon as we get to particle 239,122, this doesn't exist.
So this particle from the first model will try morphing into something that does
not exist.
And then you will not be able to do the effect.
So the main problem we need to solve is how to make them the same size.
This way, no matter what point cloud file you use, whether it's too big or too
small,
it will have the exact same amount of points.
And we can then do this effect for however many clouds we want.
So let's first start with handling the position data.
So first, we are going to want to add a point transform.
This will allow us to, for example, change the scale of all the points later on.
This is important now, but we'll get back into it in a bit.
So one way we can solve the number issue is using two fit tops.
So if we drag and then hit tab and then fit, what we can do is go to common and we
can
set the output resolution to two times.
What this does is it increases the resolution by two times.
But what's important is that if you double click, you'll see that there are now
over
a million particles, way over a million.
So we have a lot of particles.
But if we go to fit again and we hit common, we can then do output resolution to
limit
resolution and then I like using 800 by 800, but you might need to do less if your
computer
can't handle it and you can do more if your computer can't.
By doing this now we have 640,000.
So this might not seem important, but now if we copy and paste all these, then do
like
copy, paste and make our second point cloud the input, if we look at the fit 4, it
also
has 640,000.
So this way sort of standardizes how many points there are, so they are all
consistent.
So that's great.
So the last thing we want to do is for fit 1, for input smoothness and viewer
smoothness,
to nearest pixel, and we want to do the same for the other fit.
And then we want to do it for these two as well.
And that just helps with the particles looking really crisp later on when we render
it.
So now we have all of our position data sorted out, so now let's handle color.
So what we are going to want to do is hit tab and then do point file select and
drag
our point cloud right over it.
So now it's referencing it, you can see it.
And then same thing, click and do red, green and blue.
Great.
So now something is going on, they're different.
So we need to make this into color, and the way you do that is attach a map and
then you
divide by 127.
And then we do it correctly, it should be red.
There you go.
And I can explain why this is in another video, but it has something to do with how
color
values are sorted, and they're not between values 0 and 1.
So we can do the same thing with the fit trick, select both of these, Command C,
Command V,
or copy and paste, and then we should see 640,000 pixels, and that we do.
So we do the same thing, so just copy and paste this entire network, and then drag
your
second point cloud to it, and then great.
Once again we should see 640,000, and that we do.
So now we can set up for our switch system.
So go to switch, and tops, and then we need to connect the position nodes to switch,
and
then do one again for color.
So what you can do, if you're really organized, is say for example like position,
dragon,
and then color, dragon, and then similarly position, butterfly, color, butterfly.
And these naming conventions are completely arbitrary.
They can be whatever you want.
So when people tell you to type POS, COL, it's nothing to do with syntax, at least
for now.
It's just for your own discretion, whatever helps you understand it.
So if you wanted to, you could say for example, I don't know, position, drag, that
works too.
But this is just a really simple way of doing it.
So now we are going to want to attach both of our position nodes to switch with our
color
nodes into the other switch.
So now we can see in the switch one if we press P, that we have two inputs, one for
the dragon, one for the butterfly, and for color, same thing.
Important for both of them, we want to blend between inputs.
This is because, for example, if you have values between 0 and 1, let's say you
want
to morph something halfway between the dragon and the butterfly, if you blend
between inputs,
it will allow you to have a sort of blend, and that's what gives you that really
clean
morphing effect where everything switches at the same time.
Great.
And then we can sort of really neatly tie this up by adding a null.
When I first used Tush Designer, I didn't really understand why people use nulls,
but
an analogy is that you can treat them like periods in sentences.
So when you write an essay, you don't have to use periods, but it allows you to
discern
when you finish an idea and when you're starting the next one, and that's what we're
doing.
We have finished creating our system for position data and color data, so we add a
null.
And we can name it position data and color.
So that way, if we make edits in our sentence or our thoughts, then it will remain
on effect,
but at least we know that's where it ends.
So we'll come back to this in a bit.
But just so we can sort of see what's going on, we can start setting up a really
simple
render setup.
So fit a tab, go to comp, geometry, then we see this torus.
Let's get rid of that.
So double click, delete that, hit tab, go to solve, then add, and then P, and then
add
points.
So this will make it such that when we instance, we can add points, and then we
need to convert
that.
Convert, and then it should be from type, convert to particles per point, and then
particles
type render as point sprites.
And then we want to see it in both the render and the geo comp.
So purple render, blue for display.
Great.
So it looks like nothing has happened, which is expected.
So now let's add a camera, go to comp, then camera, light, then a render.
So then go to top, render, and we still see nothing, which is expected.
So now we are going to want to instance our lovely data that we prepared.
So one way we can think of instancing is that, believe it or not, each pixel on
their color
represents a coordinate in this sort of three dimensional space.
I will get to that in another video, but each pixel has its own coordinate and
geographical
position baked into it through the color.
Same thing for the actual color.
So this is the actual color that I will show.
Instead of me manually telling TouchSiner, hey, I want you to put particle two at
this
XYZ coordinate, we can just reference this and reference this really simply.
So we can do so by going to geo one, go to instance, turn instancing on, and then
translate
off is sort of like the X, Y, and Z position, so sort of like your coordinates.
So we are going to want to take our position top, drag it into translate off, then
translate
XYZ, R, G, B. Now we can see we have something, and I guess it turns out while I
was making
these models, I didn't take away the bug one, so you can enjoy two, but at least we
can
see our dragon.
Great.
And then to add color, we go to the second tab, instance two, go to the color mode,
and
drag the color top, and once again, R, G, and B. And we can see we have a red
dragon.
Cool.
So now we can adjust the sizes of these points using material, so hit tab, go to
that, and
then point sprite, and then drag it onto the geo, select the material, and then
great.
So if you go to point sprite, change the size of these particles, we can change it
here.
So you want it bigger, obviously drag it up, you want it smaller, you just drag it
down.
And great.
I think it's 0.7, looks pretty cool, so it gives that, you know what it is, but
when
it morphs, it's pretty obvious.
So great.
Now we have that.
So we now need to switch between each one really cleanly.
So now we will create our chop setup so we can do things like switch between them,
explode
the particles, and all that.
So here's how we do it.
So the first thing we're going to want to do is use chops.
So go to tab, chop, and then keyboard in.
So for keyboard in, if we select it to 1, if we hit the number 1 key, let go, it
works.
We can set this to any number, so 5 as well, it works.
You can even set it to letters, but for this video, let's just stick to 1.
So when it's morphing, there are a couple of things going on.
So first, the particles explode while still being a dragon, or the first model.
After you release the keyboard, it will switch all the coordinates, get rid of the
explosion,
and then it will morph into the second model.
So we need to sort of account for that delay, or sort of those chain of events.
So the first thing we'll do is set it so that when we hit 1, we have some number
that will
act as how much the particles explode.
So to do that, we can first use a math.
So math, put a range, and then we can set the from range and the to range, two
values
we want to use.
So what this does is, for the from range, it says, okay, from my input, this is the
range of values, and I want to scale those values to this new range, so if we hit 1,
the new max instead of 1 should be, now the max is 0.87, so if we hit 1, we have
that.
And what I mean by scale down is, for example, this part, you don't have to follow,
but let's
say we have it, right?
So now when we click it, we get the value 0.5.
Instead of the value being half of 1, it should now be half of 0.37, and if we hit
1, we can
see that work.
So that's what I mean by it's scale of the value down.
Great.
So instead of just it being like, okay, I hold the keyboard, it's immediately that
value,
we want a sort of gradient, so it happens smoothly.
So what we can do is use lag, and if you want smoother animations for anything,
this is
your go-to.
So now if we hold 1, value changes really smoothly.
So we'll see here that now there are also two values, so what do they mean?
The first one means the lag, or how long it takes to get to the value, where values
increase,
and the second one for when it decreases.
So to make this really exaggerated, let's set this to 5 and 1, and 0.1.
So what this means is that it will take five seconds for it going from 0 to 0.37,
and to
go back down to 0, it's super quick.
So if I hold 1, it will take a while to get to the max value, and when I let go, it's
really quick.
So hold 1.
As you can see, it's taking its sweet time getting to 0.37, but if we let go, it's
gone
immediately.
So it's subtle, but it's important, because for the animation visual, you want a
really
slow expansion, but a really quick morph.
So what we can do is play around with it, but I liked 0.7 and 0.2.
So once again, we can add a period to our plot, and add a null.
So now we know that this is the amplitude, and once again, this is a generic naming
convention.
You can name this whatever you want, you can leave it at null 1, but this just
makes it
such that we know, okay, this value is for the amplitude.
Great.
The second thing we need to do is now add a count.
So we need to know that when you let go of it, it will start morphing into the next
and
blend into the second input.
So we need a way to figure out, as this value decreases, it will count up 1.
So first we do a lag for really smooth values, once again, 0.5 to 0.2, and to do
the count
part we use a count chop, so count.
And then we need it to trigger on decreasing values, so set to 0.7.
So this means that when the value goes from 1 to 0, right, decreasing values, when
it
gets below 0.7, it will count up, so if we hit 1 and we release, it counts to 1.
Great.
Now, we only have two inputs, so what happens if we do it again?
We are at 0, 1, and 2, so that's not good.
So we need to clamp these values, so go to count, limit, loop min and max, and then
we
can do it to 1, and then reset them.
So now, if we hold 1, release, do it again, it will go back to the first input, 0.
And we just change this value for however many point clouds we have, so if we have
three
point clouds, so if we have three point clouds, it will be 2, so it will go from
the first
input, the second input, the third input, back to the first input.
Great.
And then, once again, just to make it a little smoother, we add another lag, we add
these
values, and then we add a null.
And then what we can do is, we can name this one index, but once again, these can
be named
whatever you want, or however it best helps you keep track and understand what
everything
is doing.
So now, if we wire them up, so go back to the switch, for index, you click on this
little
star icon, then drag it into index, you'll see it turns blue and there's an arrow
which
means it's being referenced, then similarly we drag it, great.
So now, if we hold 1, it should switch really cleanly, once we're back down, it
does, great.
So now we need the particles to explode, so here's how we do that.
So we're gonna go back to our position network, and we're gonna add a couple of
things, and
that's why it's really nice to add this dot, or not dot, this null, the act like a
period,
because now we can edit it again, and we are going to add noise.
So from the switch, drag that tab, and then hit noise, and then we see a bunch of
things
happening.
Once again, I can go into it in another video, but pretty much, whenever these
colors are
different, it means the geographical position of each particle is different.
So if we hook it up, we're gonna get something that does not look like a butterfly,
which
is good, and we control it, so undo that, and eventually we are going to add this
noise
back to our original position.
So think of it as we are adding distortion to our original position data.
So the first thing we are going to want to do is hit P, pull up the menu, output,
set
it to only noise, and then for these values, we can make it anything we want, so
please
experiment, but these are the ones that I used for the project.
Yeah, and then monochrome off, and then print the second one as well, and this
makes us
such that they're more like lines.
Great, so we can kind of see it's working, but how do we make it, if I hit 1, go,
you
know, no noise anymore, we're going to want to look at amplitude, so going back to
our
chop network, go to amp, make it active, drag it to amplitude, chop reference, and
great.
Now we see our particle equal 1, we'll see that the amplitude will change as well,
right,
so it's the first part of the chop setup, and when we release it, it will count the
position, so it will switch to a new position, while also the amplitude goes down.
So great, we hold, let go, it will change index and also get rid of this noise, so
now
we have a really clean morphing effect.
So now we are going to want to sort of change the perspective of the dragon, and we
can
do this by going to our point transform, much earlier on.
So going to go back to this, and then we can just click it so we can see in the
background.
And then one other thing is let's just select everything, or rather click render,
select
everything, go to common, and then we just want everything to look really clean, so
viewer
smoothness to nearest pixel, kind of helps out there, and then pixel format, this
just
kind of makes it like higher render or lower render, so make it 32 bit flow, great,
so
now we have a sort of like a wider color range, and that's great, so we do it again,
colors
are much more vibrant, and everything's a lot more crisp, and good.
So for this one, you know, we want to kind of like rotate it, right, so it's like,
this
one you can just kind of play around, so it's like 90, maybe like another 90, and
then
this one, I don't have like a perfect science to it, but honestly this one is
pretty cool.
And for the dragon, it's also pretty cool actually, maybe I should have just seen
this
instead, but you know, you get to just play around with alleys until you get
something
that you like, I'll see if I can get that, nice.
And then we are going to want to make it spin, so we want the box to have only the
lines,
so hit tab, material, and then go to wireframe, then drag it on, so now we have
lines, and
we can go to wireframe mode, topology, another way you can do it is tab, line, and
then drag
it on here, and this way you control things like how wide it is, how thin it is,
and a
lot more things, but wireframe is easy for now.
Okay, and then for the balls, we don't want there to be shading, at least for now,
so
we can use constant, drag it on, and then now they don't have any sort of
reflections,
and then I kind of want the box to be bigger, so we can go like 1.5, and the sphere
level
can give it smaller, so 0.03, nice, and then for the geo, we can make this a bit
smaller,
so like 0.8, and then, yeah, so now it's contained in the box, we hit 1, great, so
now our models
are inside this rotating box, and to add a background, we can do, answer operator,
transform,
and then set comp over back on color, and then the alpha to 1, and then right,
great.
Another way you can do this is like you do a constant, and then this will sort of
be
your background, to the resolution of your project, then use an over, make your
effect
over this background, and then connect it that way, and we can make this black,
great.
So yeah, now we have a morphing particle effect.
If you want to go more into the post-processing effects, the file will be in my
Patreon, which
is in the bio, but yeah, so a couple of nodes, and a little bit of chopped magic,
we have
created this really cool effect.
So you can do a lot of things too, so for example, if you want these particles to
move,
you can go to noise, trans, noise to 40, and then transform, like translate, 40,
abs time
dot second, so you can really exaggerate a number, but now it will move while that
happens.
Make it a bit more chill, nice, now it's moving really subtly, but yeah, so I hope
you enjoy
this tutorial, I hope it's the first of many, and please enjoy, thank you so much.